Now, welcome the candidates to the stage.
Vice President Kamala Harris and President Donald Trump.
Kamala Harris, is that a good debate?
Yes, you see. Have fun.
Thank you.
Welcome to you both.
It's wonderful to have you.
It's an honor to have you both here tonight.
Good evening.
We are looking forward to a spirited and thoughtful debate.
So let's get started.
I want to begin tonight with the issue
that voters repeatedly say is their number one
issue, and that is the economy and the cost of living
in this country.
Vice President Harris, you and President Trump
were elected four years ago, and your opponent
on the stage here tonight often asks his supporters,
are you better off than you were four years ago?
When it comes to the economy, do you believe Americans
are better off than they were four years ago?
So I was raised as a middle-class kid,
and I am actually the only person on this stage
who has a plan that is about lifting up the middle class
and working people of America.
I believe in the ambition, the aspirations,
the dreams of the American people.
And that is why I imagine and have actually a plan
to build what I call an opportunity economy.
Because here's the thing.
We know that we have a shortage of homes and housing,
and the cost of housing is too expensive for our
too many people.
We know that young families need support
to raise their children, and I intend on extending
a tax cut for those families of $6,000,
which is the largest child tax credit
that we have given in a long time,
so that those young families can afford to buy a crib,
buy a car seat, buy clothes for their children.
My passion, one of them, is small businesses.
I was actually, my mother raised my sister and me,
but there was a woman who helped raise us.
We call her our second mother.
She was a small business owner.
I love our small businesses.
My plan is to give a $50,000 tax deduction
to start-up small businesses,
knowing they are part of the backbone of America's economy.
My opponent, on the other hand,
his plan is to do what he has done before,
which is to provide a tax cut for billionaires
and big corporations, which will result
in $5 trillion to America's deficit.
My opponent has a plan that I call the Trump's sales tax,
which would be a 20% tax on everyday goods
that you rely on to get through the month.
Economists have said that that Trump sales tax
would actually result for middle-class families
in about $4,000 more a year,
because of his policies and his ideas
about what should be the backs of middle-class people
paying for tax cuts for billionaires.
President Trump, I'll give you two minutes.
First of all, I have no sales tax.
That's an incorrect statement.
She knows that we're doing tariffs on other countries.
Other countries are going to finally, after 75 years,
pay us back for all that we've done for the world,
and the tariff will be substantial in some cases.
I took in billions and billions of dollars,
as you know, from China.
In fact, they never took the tariff off
because it was so much money they can't.
They would totally destroy everything
that they've set out to do.
They're taking in billions of dollars from China
and other places they've left the tariffs on.
When I had it, I had tariffs, and yet I had no inflation.
Look, we've had a terrible economy
because inflation has, which is really known
as a country buster, it breaks up countries.
We have inflation like very few people have ever seen before,
probably the worst in our nation's history.
We were at 21 percent, but that's being generous
because many things are 50, 60, 70, and 80 percent higher
than they were just a few years ago.
This has been a disaster for people,
for the middle class, but for every class.
On top of that, we have millions of people
pouring into our country from prisons and jails,
from mental institutions and insane asylums,
and they're coming in and they're taking jobs
that are occupied right now by African Americans
and Hispanics and also unions.
Unions are going to be affected very soon,
and you see what's happening.
You see what's happening with towns
throughout the United States.
You look at Springfield, Ohio.
You look at Aurora in Colorado.
They are taking over the towns.
They're taking over buildings.
They're going in violently.
These are the people that she and Biden led into our country,
and they're destroying our country.
They're dangerous.
They're at the highest level of criminality,
and we have to get them out.
We have to get them out fast.
I created one of the greatest economies
in the history of our country.
I'll do it again and even better.
We are going to get to immigration and border security
during this debate, but I would like
to let Vice President Harris respond on the economy here.
Well, I would love to.
Let's talk about what Donald Trump left us.
Donald Trump left us the worst unemployment
since the Great Depression.
Donald Trump left us the worst public health epidemic
in a century.
Donald Trump left us the worst attack on our democracy
since the Civil War.
And what we have done is clean up Donald Trump's mess.
What we have done and what I intend to do
is build on what we know are the aspirations
and the hopes of the American people.
But I'm going to tell you all on this debate tonight,
you're going to hear from the same old tired playbook,
a bunch of lies, grievances, and name calling.
What you're going to hear tonight is a detailed
and dangerous plan called Project 2025
that the former president intends on implementing
if he were elected again.
I believe very strongly that the American people want
a president who understands the importance
of bringing us together.
No, we have so much more in common than what separates us.
And I pledge to you to be a president for all Americans.
President Trump will give you a minute here to respond.
Number one, I have nothing to do.
As you know, and as she knows better than anyone,
I have nothing to do with Project 2025.
That's out there. I haven't read it.
I don't want to read it purposely.
I'm not going to read it.
This was a group of people that got together.
They came up with some ideas.
I guess some good, some bad.
But it makes no difference. I have nothing to do.
Everybody knows I'm an open book.
Everybody knows what I'm going to do.
Cut taxes very substantially
and create a great economy like I did before.
We had the greatest economy. We got hit with a pandemic.
And the pandemic was not since 1917,
where 100 million people died.
Has there been anything like it?
We did a phenomenal job with the pandemic.
We handed them over a country
where the economy and where the stock market
was higher than it was before the pandemic came in.
Nobody's ever seen anything like it.
We made ventilators for the entire world.
We got gowns. We got masks.
We did things that nobody thought possible.
And people give me credit for rebuilding the military.
They give me credit for a lot of things,
but not enough credit for the great job we did
with the pandemic.
But the only jobs they got were bounce-back jobs.
These were jobs bounce-back.
And it bounced back and it went to their benefit.
But I was the one that created them.
They know it, and so does everybody else.
Vice President Harris, I'll let you respond.
So Donald Trump has no plan for you.
And when you look at his economic plan,
it's all about tax breaks for the richest people.
I am offering what I describe as an opportunity economy.
And the best economists in our country,
if not the world,
have reviewed our relative plans for the future of America.
What Goldman Sachs has said
is that Donald Trump's plan would make the economy worse.
Mine would strengthen the economy.
What the Wharton School has said is Donald Trump's plan
would actually explode the deficit.
Sixteen Nobel laureates have described his economic plan
as something that would increase inflation
and by the middle of next year would invite a recession.
You just have to look at where we are
and where we stand on the issues.
And I'd invite you to know
that Donald Trump actually has no plan for you
because he is more interested in defending himself
than he is in looking out for you.
That's just a sound bite.
They gave her that to say.
Look, I went to the Wharton School of Finance
and many of those professors, the top professors,
think my plan is a brilliant plan.
It's a great plan.
It's a plan that's going to bring up our worth,
our value as a country.
It's going to make people want to be able to go and work
and create jobs and create a lot of good, solid money
for our country.
And just to finish off, she doesn't have a plan.
She copied Biden's plan and it's like four sentences,
like run, spot, run, four sentences that are just,
oh, we'll try and lower taxes.
She doesn't have a plan.
Take a look at her plan. She doesn't have a plan.
Mr. President.